Finding aid to the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00535
Sophia Smith Collection
- Mary Chung Hayashi interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, December 15, 2006; Hayashi, Mary Chung, 1967-; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 25)
  Chung remained profoundly influenced by her sister's suicide. She chafed at the silencing effects of Asian gender and cultural norms on the one side, which enforced silence about sexual and mental health and personal matters in general, and the U.S. myth of Asians as a model minority on the other. Inspired by African American and Latina women's health activism, Chung created the National Asian Women's Health Organization (NAWHO) in 1993. The first national organization dedicated to improving the health status of Asian Pacific Islander women in the U.S., NAWHO conducts surveys, generates data, and fosters women's leadership as advocates for Asian and Pacific Islander Americans. More recently Chung founded the Iris Alliance Fund, a mental health foundation dedicated to youth suicide prevention.
  She earned a B.S. in 2000 from University of San Francisco, followed by an M.B.A. from Golden Gate University. In 2001 she married David Hayashi, a civil rights attorney. In 2006 Hayashi became the first Korean American woman elected to the California State Assembly. She is the author of Far From Home: Shattering the Myth of the Model Minority (2003).
  In this oral history Mary Chung Hayashi describes her childhood in South Korea and in the U.S. and discusses the circumstances that have led her to launch successive organizations addressing health issues in the Asian American community. She also discusses her path towards becoming the first Korean American elected to the California State Assembly. (Transcript 34 pp.)
- Amber L. Hollibaugh interviewed by Kelly Anderson, December 15-16, 2003 and January 20, 2004; Hollibaugh, Amber L., 1946-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 24)
  Amber Lynne Hollibaugh (b.1946), a "lesbian sex radical, ex-hooker, incest survivor, Gypsy child, poor-white-trash, high femme dyke," grew up in a mixed-race, working-class family near Bakersfield, California. Hollibaugh's movement politics date back to Freedom Summer in 1964 and she's been a fulltime movement activist-whether New Left, feminist, or queer-ever since. For the past two decades, Hollibaugh has been at the center of feminist debate over sexuality and a leader in the fight against AIDS. She was the founding director of the Lesbian AIDS Project at the Gay Men's Health Crisis, the first project of its kind in the nation, and produced an award-winning documentary on women living with AIDS, Heart of the Matter (1994). She is the author of My Dangerous Desires: A Queer Girl Dreaming Her Way Home (2000) and is currently the senior strategist with the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force.
  In this interview Hollibaugh details growing up in a mixed-race (Romany and Irish), working-poor family in rural California. Her family stories are incredibly rich-from tales of her grandmother Gypsy's fierce independence-and incredibly painful, from the Klan to her mother's loss of a child. Hollibaugh describes a sexually fraught and complicated adolescence, boarding school in Switzerland, dancing in Vegas and sex work in San Francisco, and finding radical politics and alternative communities. The interview focuses on themes of sexuality and politics and Hollibaugh weaves her changing consciousness and desire through the details of her marriage, coming out process, relationships, and women's movement politics. She describes SNCC, the Red Family in Berkeley and New Left politics, lesbian feminism, the sex wars and the 1982 Barnard conference, and her work in the queer movement, particularly around AIDS. Lastly, Hollibaugh talks about her life as a writer and filmmaker and about the class politics of doing both. (Transcript 166 pp.)
- Eva Kollisch interviewed by Kate Weigand, February 16-17, 2004; Kollisch, Eva, 1925-; Weigand, Kate (Box 26)
  Eva Kollisch (b. 1925) was born in Vienna. She and her siblings escaped from Nazi-led Austria via the Kindertransport in 1939 and settled with their parents in New York City in 1940. From 1942-46 Kollisch was a member of the Trotskyist organization the Workers Party, and in that role worked in factories in New York and Detroit. A 1951 graduate of Brooklyn College, Kollisch later did graduate work in German at Columbia University and joined the faculty at Sarah Lawrence College, where she co-founded the women's studies program with Gerda Lerner and Joan Kelly. In 2000 Kollisch published Girl in Movement, an autobiographical account of her years in the Workers Party. She has also written extensively about her experiences as an Austrian Jewish refugee in the U.S. Her political work includes participation in the peace and antiwar movements, the women's movement, and the movement for gay and lesbian rights.
  In this oral history Eva Kollisch describes her childhood in an upper-class Austrian Jewish family and her experiences as a young adult refugee in World War II-era New York City. The interview focuses on her socialist activism in the 1940s, her life as a bohemian wife and mother during the 1950s, her political reawakening in the 1960s, her personal and professional experiences as a feminist and lesbian professor at Sarah Lawrence College, and her participation in the peace movement, the feminist movement, and the gay and lesbian movement. Kollisch's story illustrates the complex relationships among identity, political activism, and the larger political context, and the activities that radical activists undertake in both periods of political upheaval and political downturn. (Transcript 57 pp.)
- Marian Kramer interviewed by Loretta Ross, 2014 February 1-2; Kramer, Marian; Ross, Loretta J.; 1 oral histories (video interview and transcript)
  Marian Kramer (b. 1944) has been involved in welfare rights and civil rights activism since the 1960s. Kramer's activism centers the experiences of poor women and families. Recently, she has led the charge against the privatization of water in Detroit, Michigan. Kramer, along with other organizers, was arrested for disorderly conduct, trying to physically keep city trucks from shutting down citizens' access to water. Much of her work has gone towards defending victims of unjust claims of "welfare fraud." Kramer is the co-chair of the National Welfare Rights Union, and, over the years, has held key positions in a number of other activist and non-profit organizations.
  In this interview Marian Kramer talks about developing an understanding of injustice and racism as a young girl growing up in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and Dallas, Texas. Kramer remembers some of her early experiences organizing and participating in successful economic boycotts. Her drive for activism led her to drop out of school and become a full time organizer with the Congress of Racial Equality, as well as talking in detail about her first arrest. Kramer talks about the development of social, class, and racial consciousness in young organizers, and provides invaluable insight into the successful strategies and lived experiences of a lifelong organizer. Kramer details her transition to advocating for Welfare Rights, and her introduction to water access work.
  This interview is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
  - Video interview of Marian Kramer, 1 oral histories (13 video files transferred from miniDV tapes)
  - Transcript of interview of Marian Kramer
- Gerda Lerner interviewed by Nancy MacLean, September 12-13, 2003; Lerner, Gerda, 1920-; MacLean, Nancy (Box 27)
  Gerda Lerner (b. 1920) is a long-time peace and civil rights activist and pioneer in the creation of the academic discipline of women's history. Her writings include The Majority Finds its Past: Placing Women in History (1979), The Creation of Patriarchy (1980), The Creation of Feminist Consciousness from the Middle Ages to Eighteen-Seventy (1996), and Fireweed: A Political Autobiography (2002).
  This audio-only interview focuses on Lerner's grassroots organizing through the Congress of American Women in the post-World War II years, the relationship of the Congress to the Communist Party, and the evolution of Lerner's political thought from Marxism to feminism. (Transcript 92 pp.)
- Barbara Love interviewed by Kelly Anderson, March 6, 2008; Love, Barbara; Anderson, Kelly (Box 28)
  Barbara J. Love (b. 1937) was raised in New Jersey, graduated from Syracuse University in 1959, and worked as a business magazine editor for most of her professional career. She is an activist and writer, co-author with Sidney Abbott of Sappho Was a Right-On Woman (1972) and editor of Feminists Who Changed America, 1963-1975 (2006).
  In this oral history, Love reflects on her childhood and family of origin, her introduction to lesbian life and politics, and her activism in the 1970s. This interview pays particular attention to the National Organization for Women, the Houston conference in 1977, Radicalesbians, and her published writings. (Transcript 43 pp.)
- Anne MacKay interviewed by Kelly Anderson, September 21, 2003; MacKay, Anne; Anderson, Kelly (Box 29)
  Anne MacKay (b.1928) is a retired teacher who has spent most of her life in New York City and Orient, NY. MacKay taught theater at Dalton and Horace Mann Schools and retired in 1992. Her activism began with her first Daughters of Bilitis meeting in 1969. Most of MacKay's feminist engagement has been "community" oriented rather than "political," in her words. A writer, poet, and theater producer, MacKay put together a number of lesbian musicals and published two books: Wolf Girls at Vassar: Lesbian and Gay Experiences 1930-1990 (St. Martin's Press, 1993) and She Went A-Whaling, The Whaling Journal of Martha Brown (Oysterponds Historical Society, 1993). She is one of the founders of the Lesbian & Gay Alumnae of Vassar College and has been involved in other community organizations, including the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, the Lesbian Herstory Archives, the Astraea Foundation, and the North Fork Women for Women Fund (NFWFWF). MacKay has been a crucial community builder in Orient, New York, and has been very active with NFWFWF.
  The oral history focuses on MacKay's involvement in the North Fork lesbian community, including NFWFWF, and her work in community theater production. She also reflects on her childhood, family background, and coming of age sexually. Because this interview is intended as a complement to MacKay's papers housed at the SSC (which include an unpublished memoir,) our discussion of her earlier years is light. (Transcript 45 pp.)
- Betita Martinez interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, March 3, 2006 and August 6, 2006; Martinez, Betita, 1925; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 30)
  Elizabeth (Betita) Martinez was born December 12, 1925. As the child of a dark-skinned Mexican-born father and a white Euro-American mother, Betita met discrimination as she was growing up in segregated Washington, D.C.
  During World War II, Martinez attended Swarthmore College, where she was the only non-white student on campus. After graduation in 1946, she worked at the newly-established United Nations, where she researched decolonization efforts and strategies. In the late 1950s she became an editor at Simon & Schuster, and later Books and Arts Editor of The Nation magazine. She also became active in the U.S. civil rights movement, directing the New York office of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and participating in SNCC's Freedom Summer in Mississippi in 1964.
  From 1968 to 1976, Martinez lived in New Mexico where she became founding editor of El Grito del Norte (The Cry of the North), a monthly community newspaper that linked the Chicano land movement to similar struggles around the world. She served as founding director of the Chicano Communications Center in Albuquerque to teach Chicanos about history and contemporary issues.
  After moving to California in 1976, Martinez joined the Democratic Workers Party, a Marxist group led by women, and became involved in Central American solidarity work, local struggles for social justice, and grassroots organizing to save public services. In 1982 she ran for Governor on the Peace and Freedom Party ticket. In addition to teaching ethnic studies and women's studies on several campuses, she traveled extensively to observe efforts to create socialist societies. Her travels included trips to China, the Soviet Union, Vietnam, Hungary, and Poland, in addition to several trips to Cuba beginning in 1959. In 1997 Martinez co-founded the Institute for Multiracial Justice which promotes alliances among communities of color on a range of issues. She edited the Institute's newsletter, Shades of Power.
  Martinez' publications include The Movement (1963) and Letters from Mississippi (1965; reissued 2002), and De Colores Means All of Us: Latina Views for a Multi-Colored Century (1998). Her bilingual book Five Hundred Years of Chicano History, first issued in 1976 as 450 Years of Chicano History, is in its sixth edition. She is completing another bilingual book, Five Hundred Years of Chicana History, a pictorial survey [published 2008]. She is a frequent contributor to anthologies, including The Feminist Memoir Project, and to Z and other progressive magazines.
  Martinez has received numerous awards for her social justice work. In 2005 she was a nominee for the 1000 Women for the Nobel Peace Prize. Martinez lives in San Francisco where she continues to write, lecture, edit and teach.
  After a brief first marriage, Martinez married Hans Koning, author of 40 fiction and nonfiction books. In 1954 they had a daughter, Tessa, before divorcing. Tessa, an actress, lives in San Francisco.
  This oral history offers a general overview of Martinez' life and work. Martinez reviews her childhood and her political experiences from SNCC forward. She discusses the difficulty of sustaining left groups in the face of sectarianism and government infiltration. Martinez comments on current domestic and international politics and reflects on tensions between her activism and her role as a single parent. (Transcript 70 pp.)
- Luz Alvarez Martinez interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, December 6-7, 2004; Martinez, Luz Alvarez, 1943-; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 31)
  Luz Alvarez Martinez (b. 1943) grew up one of twelve children of Mexican immigrant parents in San Leandro, California, in the Bay Area. Her father was a carpenter, and the family spent summers in farmworker camps harvesting crops. Luz graduated from St. Elizabeth's (Catholic) High School in 1960. She married in 1964 and had four sons, combining childrearing with community support for farmworker organizing. She divorced in 1981.
  In the late 1970s, Martinez began college study to become a nurse midwife. She became involved in the Berkeley Women's Health Collective, serving on the board and helping to establish its women of color clinic. Inspired by the health activism of African American women, especially the 1983 Spelman conference, Martinez co-founded the National Latina Health Organization in 1986, the first national organization by and for Latinas working on health issues and using the Self-Help framework pioneered by the National Black Women's Health Project. Martinez also came to incorporate indigenous dance and mestiza spirituality into her community organizing. Among women of color she championed lesbian issues, and within mainstream reproductive rights groups she advanced a broad health agenda; she served on the board of the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL).
  Martinez was active in early efforts to form and sustain multiracial coalitions among Latina, Native American, Asian Pacific American, and African American women in the late 1980s and early 1990s. At the 1994 International Conference on Population and Development in Cairo, she played a key role in asserting the standing of U.S. women of color as representatives of underdeveloped communities. She participated in the Fourth World Conference for Women in Beijing in 1995 as well. In 1997 she became a co-founder of the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective. In 2005, Martinez retired from the National Latina Health Organization. She is currently president of the Hispanic United Fund.
  In this oral history, Martinez describes her childhood immersed in the Catholic culture of Mexican immigrants in California. She describes an emotionally difficult marriage. She traces her decades of political work and details current programs of the National Latina Health Organization. Martinez recounts moments of cooperation and tension between women of color and mainstream women's groups as well as among women of color. Her story underscores the centrality of Self-Help to her life and work. (Transcript 98pp).
  The Luz Alvarez Martinez Papers and the Undivided Rights Book Project Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Geraldine Miller interviewed by Loretta Ross, October 14, 2004; Miller, Geraldine, 1920-2005; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 32)
  Geraldine Miller (1920-2005) was born in Sabetha, Kansas. In 1971 she founded the Household Technicians' Union for domestic workers in New York City, which won the national right for domestic workers to be covered by the Federal Minimum Wage Act. She is past president of the National Congress of Neighborhood Women and founding president of the Bronx Chapter of the National Organization for Women. As an early African American feminist, she received many awards for her tireless activism on behalf of domestic workers. With a story spanning eight decades, Miller pioneered work that crossed boundaries of race, class and gender and demonstrated the power of working-class women in the feminist movement.
  In this oral history Geraldine Miller describes her life as an African American child born in the Midwest in the 1920s. As a child of incest between her mother and her mother's stepfather, Miller focuses on her struggle to lift herself out of poverty, overcome the murder of her mother, and launch her career as a national organizer of domestic workers and leading feminist with the National Organization for Women and the National Congress of Neighborhood Women. (Transcript 79 pp.)
  The National Congress for Neighborhood Women Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections. Another oral history of Miller can be found in the New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project.
- Cherríe Moraga interviewed by Kelly Anderson, June 6-7, 2005; Moraga, Cherríe, 1952-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 33)
  Cherríe Moraga, born in Los Angeles in 1952, is a poet, playwright, and cultural activist whose commitment to liberation struggles spans three decades. Moraga earned a BA in 1974 from Immaculate Heart College and an MA in Feminist Studies from San Francisco State in 1980. After a brief period in New York City (and the birth of Kitchen Table Press), Moraga returned to her California roots, turning her creative energy and political vision towards playwriting, including a six year residency with San Francisco's Brava Theater. Her award-winning plays include "Watsonville: Some Place Not Here," "Heroes and Saints," and "The Hungry Woman: A Mexican Medea." Moraga has also published extensively as an essayist and poet. She is best known for the groundbreaking anthology This Bridge Called My Back: Writings by Radical Women of Color (1981), co-edited with Gloria Anzaldúa and winner of the Before Columbus Award in 1986, and Loving in the War Years: Lo Que Nunca Pasó Por Sus Labios (1983). She is currently the Artist-in-Residence in the Departments of Drama and Spanish & Portuguese at Stanford University and resides in Oakland with her partner Celia and her son Rafael.
  In this oral history Moraga describes growing up with a Mexicana mother and an Anglo father, discusses the significance of family to her life and work, and reflects upon the nuances of race, class, language and skin color. Moraga talks about her own politicization and her introduction to and sustained leadership in liberation struggles. The interview focuses on Moraga's involvement with the women's movement and feminisms, and her cultural activism, particularly around This Bridge and Kitchen Table Press. Moraga concludes with a discussion of her current work as a writer, her commitment to teaching and to young people of color, and to creating familia. (Transcript 89 pp.)
- Aurora Levins Morales interviewed by Kelly Anderson, September 28 and 30, 2005; Morales, Aurora Levins, 1954; Anderson, Kelly (Box 35)
  Aurora Levins Morales was born in Indiera, Puerto Rico in 1954 to a Puerto Rican mother and Jewish father. Raised on the island and then in Chicago, Levins Morales was surrounded by political debate and intellectual engagement. The youngest member of the Chicago Women's Liberation Union, Levins Morales became an activist at an early age. Levins Morales relocated to the San Francisco Bay Area in the mid-70s where she immediately connected with movement organizations like the Puerto Rican Socialist Party and New Jewish Agenda and radical cultural groups like La Peña and the Berkeley Women's Center. A poet and writer, Levins Morales work has been widely recognized among both North American feminist and Puerto Rican literary traditions. She was a contributor to This Bridge Called My Back (1983) and in 1986 published Getting Home Alive in collaboration with her mother, Rosario Morales. Levins Morales has written a prose poetry book on the history of Puerto Rican and related women and a collection of essays. Her fiction, poetry and non-fiction have been widely anthologized. She is recognized as an important contemporary Puerto Rican writer. As a historian, she has focused on documenting the history of Puerto Ricans in California through oral histories, collection of archival materials, and an exhibit. Levins Morales is active in Middle east peace work and the disability/chronic illness liberation movement. She is currently working on a novel and lives in Berkeley, California.
  In this oral history, Levins Morales details her family heritage and describes her childhood in Puerto Rico, particularly in relation to her parents' political activism and Communist party membership. The majority of the interview focuses on Levins Morales activism, her experiences as a woman of color in both male-led nationalist organizations and the predominantly white, middle-class feminist movement, and her work as a writer and educator. (Transcript 101 pp.)
- Rosario Morales interviewed by Kelly Anderson, January 29-30, 2005; Morales, Rosario, 1930-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 35)
  The daughter of Puerto Rican immigrants, Rosario Morales (b. 1930) was raised in el barrio of New York City. In 1949, Morales joined the Communist Party and married Richard Levins, the son of Ukrainian Jewish immigrants and a scientist. Together they moved to Puerto Rico in 1951 where they became active in the Puerto Rican Communist Party and the Fellowship of Reconciliation while working a small farm in the mountains. They eventually returned to the U.S., first to Chicago then to Cambridge, but the people and culture of Puerto Rico remained at the center of Morales' work. Morales and her daughter Aurora Levins Morales became active in the women's movement in the late 60s, were a part of the Chicago Women's Liberation Union, and co-authored a book of poetry and prose called Getting Home Alive in 1986. Morales is recognized as a major contemporary Puerto Rican writer.